Muhammad Umar Ramadhana

Jakarta, Indonesia

Email: umarkotak@yahoo.co.id

Linkedin: linkedin.com/in/muhammad-umar-ramadhana-476083141

Web: https://mumarr.vercel.app

Summary

I am a backend developer with ~5 years of experience. I also have enough knowledge of frontend development. I previously worked on a product related to hospitality and entertainment. Apart from that, I also maintain multiple personal projects that I personally use on a day to day basis - full list of projects can be seen on my website.

Experience

Back End Engineer Lead

Everywhere.ID

Web: https://play.everywhere.id Sep 2023 - Present (9 months)

everywhere.id - previously GoPlay under GOTO

Design 2 ways online to offline entertainment systems. playbox provides content creators a way to perform in multiple places at once. Imagine a creator from Jakarta, can play in multiple cafes at once. The creator can also see the venue situation through the camera provided in the play box. This also allows the creator to receive gift from multiple places at once using virtual gift features.

Works:

- Leading a team of 2 engineers
- System design and requirements gathering
- Improving play everywhere schedule management and reliability (which creator should perform when and where)
- Developing a picture in picture feature allows visitors on playbox in cafe A to see visitors on playbox in cafe B, imagine you can see through the other side of a portal.
- Migrate infrastructure from Google Cloud to Tencent Cloud
- Make internal tools to manage k8s ENV using Kubeseal https://github.com/umarkotak/go-kubeseal-gui

Founder & Full Stack Engineer

Bukukaskita

Web: https://bukukaskita.netlify.app
Jun 2021 - Present (3 years)

Bukukaskita is a web application for managing your family expenses

Features:

Record daily transaction, Voice to transaction, Receipt image to transaction, Dashboard to show current balance of each wallets, Statistical dashboard, Investing simulation, Budgeting, Gold prices wallet with loss and gain tracker, Wealth asset management.

Go Play Back End Tech Lead

Gojek - GOTO Web: N/A

Nov 2022 - Sep 2023 (11 months)

Works:

- design and migrate Goplay social login flow on top of existing Gojek auth flow with 0 down time
- managing team member, task analysis, task breakdown, RnD and task distribution
- design refund mechanism for existing token top up flow
- build live features (audience list, badges, missions, payout for agency, etc)
- managing web socket for controlling live stream
- design multi streaming feature with agora, and forward to other live provider using rtmp protocol
- design multi chat integration with external provider; eg youtube, FB live chat
- develop play everywhere box, an interactive offline live stream box with camera
- ads management

Go Play Back End Developer

Gojek - GOTO Web: N/A

Jul 2020 - Sep 2023 (3 years 3 months)

Goplay is an entertainment product that is under Gojek. We provide video on demand (VOD), a live platform for content creators, and the recent product is play everywhere. This product's main goal is enabling Indonesian content creators to make money online and can achieve sustainability by themself.

Works:

- create beacon, an internal tool for tracking user action.
- create payout feature using midtrans IRIS, this allows creators to pull out the money they receive from the audience.
- analysis and build features such as: order for gifting, revenue and payout, tracking, analytic reporting, identity service, social login, alerting etc.

Go Life Back End Developer

Gojek - GOTO

Web: N/A

May 2018 - Jul 2020 (2 years 3 months)

Golife is a lifestyle service provider. We provide services such as go massage (where a therapist is assigned and then directed to your location), go glam (a beautician), go clean (a cleaner), etc. we have thousands of daily active users and hundreds of concurrent orders during our peak time, eg: on weekends.

Works:

- Build various features for Goplay such as: notification system, booking, product discovery, address history, user review and feedback, discount, vouchering, alerting, etc.
- Initiating marvin, a supermarket app. It allows you to buy daily necessities and then will be delivered to your home.
- Initiate the practice of making tech documentation as a source of truth for all discussion.

PIC Back End Go Life Service Marketplace

Gojek - GOTO Web: N/A

Feb 2019 - Aug 2019 (7 months)

GoLife Service Marketplace is a platform where life service providers such as massage parlor, automotive garage, etc can list themself on the platform. This allows their location to be easily discovered by the GoLife users. Users can also make a booking and make a payment through the marketplace.

I am in charge of designing and maintaining GoLife Service Marketplace Backend.

Works:

- Design all the system for service marketplace (ordering, partner listing, payment, etc)
- Setting up the initial Infrastructure
- End to end products flow design

Trainee

Gojek - GOTO Web: N/A

Jan 2018 - Apr 2018 (4 months)

- Learn public speaking.
- Learn basic programming and practices, pair programming, tdd, DRY, etc.
- Learn Devops, infrastructure provisioning and automation.
- Learn Data science, data analysis and extraction.

Basic Computer Lab Assistant

Institute Technology PLN

Web: N/A

Feb 2015 - Feb 2018 (3 years 1 month)

- Assist students learning basic programming, eg: c++, c#, php, java, python
- Build a web portal to help students on a daily basis. Reporting, giving latest laboratory information, sharing files, collecting tasks, scoring tasks, and generating reports.
- Maintain a computer laboratory, annually cleaning up the hardwares, maintain computer performance, set up the local network, set up a local web server.

Bootcamp Participant

Kolla Web: N/A

Oct 2017 - Dec 2017 (3 months)

Learn: golang, ruby on rails, postgres, git, kafka Output:

- Simple online ride sharing application using rails and kafka
- Caching location service using golang

Projects

Bukukaskita

Web: https://bukukaskita.netlify.app

Bukukaskita is an app to keep track of your daily expenses. It has various other features related to finance such as: investment calculator, gold price tracker, ease of use when tracking transactions (you can input transaction data using image or voice).

YTKIDD

Web: https://ytkidd.vercel.app

YTKIDD is a Youtube alternative for kids. The content listed in YTKIDD is manually curated, so it should not recommend any video outside of the list. YTKIDD also has a quiz feature so that your kids need to answer the quiz first before starting watching. YTKIDD is still in active development mode. I plan to add more features that can help my kids to learn.

VDUB

Repo: https://github.com/umarkotak/vdub

VDUB is a tool to automatically dub youtube videos which contain English monologue into Indonesia. This app idea comes from when I see a lot of good english videos on youtube, but it is using English language, hence I need to translate it in order for my kids to also watch it.

Neng-Gemini

Web: https://neng-qemini.vercel.app

A simple web app to converse with google gemini Al. Again, this web is targeted to my kids. Sometimes I don't know the answer when my kids ask me questions. With the help of generative Al, hopefully that question can be answered.

Skills

Golang, Ruby, Javascript, Python, PHP, Java, Ruby on Rails, Reactjs, Nextjs, Postgresql, Mongodb, Redis, Firebase, Elasticsearch, Kafka, Cloud computing.

Education

Institute Technology PLN

Bachelor of Technology - Information Technology 2014 - 2018

Final project: Steganography web application to sign certificate using Least Significant Bit (LSB)

SMAN 2 Cibinong

High School - Science 2011 - 2014